# **Maryam Arab**

Ph.D. student

Department of Computer Science Volgenau School of Engineering George Mason University

4400 University Drive, MS 4A5, Fairfax, VA 22030

marab@gmu.edu maryam.arab83@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/maryam-arab http://mason.gmu.edu/~marab

### Research Area

I am investigating how human computer interaction would be effective in designing programming tool and how to blend machine and human intelligence.

I explored ways to describe programming skills more explicitly through programming strategies through a specific sequence of steps a developer can follow to successfully finish a programming task.

#### What I have done so far

I presented a novel notation for designing a programming language and a novel tool that explicitly represent programming strategies and frame executing strategies as a collaborative effort between human abilities to make decisions and computer abilities to structure process and persist information. I tested this tool with 28 users with 2 expert strategies. The evaluation showed potential benefits in terms of being more successful, organized, systematic, better performing in finishing the assigned development task.

Next, I evaluated how we can help expert developers share their expertise by writing down their strategies and what difficulties they faced.

Extracting and keeping expert strategies brings up the hope of the possibility of extracting the accumulated strategic knowledge and rules of experts and then using this knowledge to train future experts. It might bring up a whole set of explicit programming strategies that can be used in schools or on personal training and will reduce the decade of experience and training required for people to become elite programmers.

#### **Research Interests**

Software tools design and development Human-computer interaction Datamining

## **Employment**

George Mason University

**Research Assistant** 

Department of Computer Science

George Mason University

**Teacher Assistant** 

Department of Computer Science

May 2016 - August 2016

January 2017-May 2017

Jun 2017 -Present

**Nexus Direct** 

Intern

Design and development of WordPress website Develop theme and custom fields for the website

Old Dominion University

January 2014 - August 2016

**Graduate Research Assistant**Department of Computer Science

Agah Information Co.

April 2013 - Jun 2014

Maryam Arab **CURRICULUM VITAE** 

**Software Engineer** 

Design and development of "I Shop" (Java, Grails, Groovy)

Graphic and UI Designer (HTML, ¡Query)

Website design and development (WordPress, PHP)

Aryans Arzeshpardaz Investment Consulting Co.(AAICCO) October 2011 - April 2013

Software Developer, Network Admin

Designed and implemented holding software system (C#)

Developed company's evaluation system (C#)

Developed portfolio management system (Java, Grails, Groovy)

Automated Test (Asp .Net) **Network Maintenance** 

Shaven Informatics Co. October 2007 - November 2011

**Software Developer** Designed and developed "Sharif University of Technology" Card

printer system (C#)

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science January 2017- Present

August 2014 - August 2016

August 2002-February 2007

George Mason University Advisor: Thomas Latoza

**Master in Computer Science** 

Old Dominion University Thesis: Detecting On-street parking spaces using pedestrian cellphone

Magnetometer internal sensor

Propose a sensor based Mobile application for detecting the curb side

parking spot

Design a Mobile application to detect the street lane number in which

the car is driven

Advised by Tamer Nadeem

**B.S.** in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Department of Engineering

Tehran Markaz University

**Technical Skills** 

**Platforms** Ubuntu Linux, Windows, Mac

**Programming Skills** Java, Android, C#, C++, ASP.net, PHP, Groovy

**Web Development** HTML, CSS, JavaScript, XML, Grails, JQuery, JSON, Spring Framework,

Hibernate, Spring MVC

**Software Development** 

Methodologies

Agile, OOAD, UML

**Software Development** 

Server, SharePoint Server, CVS, SVN, JUnit, Git

IntelliJ Idea, Eclipse, MS Visual Studio .Net, Android Studio, Team Foundation

Tools

**Database Management** 

MySQL, MS SQL Server, Firebase

**Systems** 

**Publications** 

[C3] Thomas D. LaToza, Maryam Arab, Dastyni Loksa, and Andrew J. Ko – Explicit Programming Strategies- ESE-2019(under revision)

- [C2] Maryam Arab, Tamer Nadeem. MagnoPark Locating On-Street Parking Spaces Using Magnetometer-Based Pedestrians' Smartphones. SECON 2017: 1-9
- [C1] Jing He, Dong Si, Maryam Arab. Detection of Secondary Structures from 3D Protein Images of Medium Resolutions and its Challenges. ICIG (2) 2015: 147-155